A Guide to the Donald S. Wallace Collection, 1943-1970
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Donald S. Wallace Collection, 1943-1970
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2009-101
1 box; 1.1 cu. ft.
The collection contains a selection of Wallace's professional correspondence, U.S. Geological Survey Reports, Virginia state agency and local reports, and photographs from sites around the state.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Donald S. Wallace Collection was purchased by Special Collections in June 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Little biographical information is available on Donald S. Wallace. He worked as an engineer for the U.S. Geological Survey Water Resources Division until at least 1952, including several months on the Water Resources Committee and a related subcommittee. Wallace served as Commissioner of the Water Resources Division during his tenure, as well.
In 1926, the Virginia Division of Water Resources and Power was established. The name changed to the Virginia Division of Water Resources in 1943. Eventually, the division came under the control of the Virginia Department of Conservation and Economic Development until it ceased to exist as a single agency. Much of the same work is now under the jurisdiction of the Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation and the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (established in 1993). Additional materials in the collection relate to the Virginia State Water Control Board, initially established in 1946 and now a part of the Virginia Department of Conservation and Recreation.
Scope and Content
The collection contains a selection of Wallace's professional correspondence, U.S. Geological Survey Reports, Virginia state agency and local reports, and photographs from sites around the state.
A majority of the correspondence, dating 1943-1945 and 1951-1952, consists of letters received as carbon copies. The collection contains only a few letters to or by Wallace. As much of the correspondence relates to the drafting of division documents, enclosures are attached, including annotated versions of documentation and hand-drawn maps. The photographs depict a number of sites. Only a portion of them are identified, specifically those taken around the Roanoke and Smith Rivers in Virginia.
The collection contains several series of reports from 1943 to 1970, described in further detail below. There are published and unpublished U.S. Geological Survey reports about different regions in Virginia; published Virginia state agency reports; and county and local agency and individual reports. Most of the county and local reports were written by engineers or engineering firms from Virginia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: Series I: Correspondence, Series II: Photographs, Series III: U.S. Geological Survey Reports, Series IV: Virginia State Agency Reports, and Series V: Local Reports.
Series I: Correspondence contains business correspondence from portions of Wallace's tenure with the Virginia Water Resources Division. Any enclosure are attached to the original correspondence. The 1943-1945 correspondence relates to trips and projects throughout Virginia. Much of it is copies of letters sent to individuals other than Wallace. Several of the letters were written by William M. McGill, the Assistant State Geologist during the period. Letters and memoranda from 1951-1952 are concerned with the creation of the Water Resources Committee and include drafts of committee documentation. The committee was disbanded, along with other state committees, due to lack of funding, in late 1952. Of particular interest is a thank you note to Wallace from Governor John S. Battle (October 15, 1952) in appreciation for his service with the committee.
Series II: Photographs contains a collection of approximately 80 items. In most cases, the negative image is available as well. The photographs have been left in their original order and the negatives placed with the matching images. Most of the photographs are not identified. The collection of 3¼ x 4½ photographs have handwritten captions on the back, identifying the sites along the Roanoke River near Buggs Island. Other select images with captions include such sites as the Appomattox River, the Smith River near Philpott, Virginia, and the Shenandoah River. Based on the few dated images and dates in the collection, the photographs were most likely taken in the 1940s.
Series III: U.S. Geological Survey Reports contains a collection of published and unpublished reports relating to water in Virginia. The unpublished reports are written on specific rivers or flood regions in the state. Topics of published reports include water resource investigations, flood reports, and streamflow analysis. While all the reports in this series were distributed by the U.S. Geological Survey, several were written in conjunction with Virginia agencies or local Department of the Interior employees.
Series IV: Virginia State Agency Reports contains seven published reports. Two are on specific regions (the James and York River Basins), and the remainder deal with aspects of water in Virginia (surface water and water and mineral resources). Most of the reports were created by the Virginia Department of Conservation and Economic Development, Division of Water Resources.
Series V: Local Reports contains several consulting reports by independent engineers or engineering groups. Areas covered include Augusta, Bath, Chesterfield, and Fairfax counties, and the city of Alexandria. This series also contains a collection of reports entitled, "Results of spring trip, August 1962." Each report consists of several pages of spring locations and related data. The following Virginia counties have reports: Alleghany, Augusta, Bath, Botetourt, Craig, Frederick, Highland, Page, Rockbridge, Rockingham, and Shenandoah.
Index Terms
Persons:
Battle, John Stewart, 1890-1972.; McGill, William M.; Wallace, Donald S.
Corporate Names:
Geological Survey (U.S.). Water Resources Division.; Virginia. Dept. of Conservation and Economic Development.; Virginia. Division of Water Resources.; Virginia. Division of Water Resources and Power.
Geographical Names:
Roanoke River (Va. and N.C.).; Appomattox River (Va.).; Smith River (Va.).
Contents List
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE, 1943-1952.
  - Correspondence, 1943-1945. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952. (Box-folder 1:2)
- SERIES II: PHOTOGRAPHS, [c.1940s].
  - Photographs–unidentified. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Photographs–Roanoke River, Virginia. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Photographs–unidentified. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Photographs–unidentified. (Box-folder 1:6)
- SERIES III: U.S. GEOLOGICAL SURVEY REPORTS, 1950-1970.
  Arrangement note: Publications are listed by alphabetically by author, regardless of publication status.
  Series note: Call numbers for circulating copies are listed in bold after the title of the publication. Items labeled "Newman Library Storage" must be requested in advance through the Library's catalog, Addison.
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "Dan River near Turbeville, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics at U.S. Highway 58." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1953. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "Jackson River at Lowmoor, VA: Flow Characteristics at Proposed Channel Change U.S. Highway 60." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1954. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "Mattaponi River near Bowling Green, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics at State Highway 207." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1953. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "Mattaponi River at Route 207, near Bowling Green, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1952. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "North River at Rockland Mill Church near Weyers Cave, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics at State Highway 276." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1956. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "Nottoway River near Stony Creek, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics at U.S. Highway 301." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1955. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). "South River at Waynesboro, VA: Flood-Flow Characteristics at U.S. Highway 250." Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1953. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). Water Resources Investigations in Virginia. Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1963. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.). Water Resources Investigations in Virginia, 1969. Washington: U.S. Geological Survey, 1969. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.), and United States. Flood Insurance Study for Alexandria, Virginia: Cameron Run Flood Plain Area. [Washington, D.C.]: The Survey, 1966. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.), and Virginia. "Peak Discharges for the Rockbridge County Flood of September 10, 1950." Charlottesville, Va: U.S. Geological Survey, 1950. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Geological Survey (U.S.), and Virginia. Virginia Water Resources Summary. Richmond, Va: U.S. Geological Survey, September 1970. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Newman Library Storage: HD1694.V8 U53
  - Nuckels, E. H. Virginia Streamflow Data Program Analysis. Richmond, Va: U.S. Geological Survey, Water Resources Division, 1970. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Tice, Richard H. "Magnitude and Frequency of Floods in the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia." Charlottesville, Va: U.S. Geological Survey, 1950. (Box-folder 1:11)
- SERIES IV: VIRGINIA STATE AGENCY REPORTS, 1959-1970.
  Arrangement note: Publications are listed by alphabetically by author.
  - Virginia. James River Basin Comprehensive Water Resources Plan, 1969. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Newman Library Storage: TC424.V8 A3 no.214
  - Virginia. Notes on Surface Water in Virginia. Richmond: The Division, 1960. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Newman 3rd Floor: GB1225.V8 A513
  - Virginia. Notes on Surface Water in Virginia. Richmond: The Division, 1965. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Virginia. Virginia Minerals. Charlottesville, Va: Division of Geology, February 1967. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Newman 5th Floor: TN24.V8 A37
  - Virginia. Water Resources of Virginia. Report. 1952. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Newman Library Storage: TC424.V8 A5 1952
  - Virginia. York River Basin Comprehensive Water Resources Plan. 1970. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Virginia State Soil Conservation Committee. Water Resources of Virginia; Progress Report. 1959. (Box-folder 1:15)
- SERIES V: LOCAL REPORTS, 1943-1969.
  Arrangement note: Reports are listed by alphabetically by author.
  - Alvord, Burdick, and Howson Engineers. "Report to the Board of Supervisors of Bath County, Virginia on Water Supply for the Warm Springs Valley, December 1947." Chicago, 1947. (3 copies) (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Chester Engineers. "Alexandria, Virginia: Analysis Report and Computations of Normal Maximum Flood Stage on the Lower Reaches of Four Mile Run." Pittsburgh, PA, 1943. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - "Fairfax County Water Authority 1969 Annual Report." Annandale, VA, 1969. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Hale, John S. "Report on the Hydrology of the Coles Run Area: South River Sanitary District, Augusta County, Virginia." Staunton, VA, 1948. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - "Results of Springs Trip, August 1962." 1962. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Wiley & Wilson. "Engineering Report on $1,100,000 Bond Issue Water Supply Improvements: Chesterfield County, Virginia." Lynchburg, VA, 1950. (Box-folder 1:20)